Now, okay, y'all have been killing me in
the comments, okay, about this whole
Amanda Seals self-diagnosing. So, I
feel, okay, let's talk about the
repercussions of self-diagnosing. Is it
a bad thing? Did she hurt herself by
lying in some people's eyes and not
taking accountability? So, let's get
into it.
If you are new here, I'm Anthony
Spearman, a licensed marriage and family
therapist, and I see a lot of clients
who are on the spectrum, who do not know
they're on the spectrum. And now later
on in life, they're recognizing and
realizing, maybe through my work, maybe
through things they see on TikTok,
things like that, that they might be
someone living on the spectrum or having
some type of neurological,
neurodivergent,
something that they're living with,
okay? Okay. Now, there is one side of
the hill where people feel like
self-diagnosing is trash. It's terrible.
You should not do it.
And there's other people on the other
side of it that's like, okay,
I finally know what this thing is that's
been affecting me. I finally figured it
out through Google, through TikTok,
through seeing and living
examples of people living with this. It
makes sense to me now, okay?
Now, Amanda Seals is someone who in a
lot of people's eyes is problematic, a
professional victim, I've heard, doesn't
take accountability, is now just using
this label to make excuses for the way
she acts. And depending on what you
think about Amanda, you're going to fall
into one of those categories, okay?
Either you think she's like a great
person, or you think she's terrible. In
the society that we live in, it's very
black or white. There's not a lot of
gray that exists in the year 2024
anymore. I'm going to tell you that
right now, okay? Now, me as a therapist
looking at it, I see how someone who
self-diagnoses themselves can benefit
from self-diagnosing. And I often ask
this question in my comments on that
video
that I'm going to seal's video
what is the difference between
self-diagnosing yourself with autism and
self-diagnosing yourself with
depression?
And I have still not got an answer.
Okay, do I think it's problematic that
she got on a platform and self-diagnosed
in front of millions upon millions of
people? In some eyes, it is problematic.
I'm not going to cap. It can be
problematic because it makes it look
like at time someone can just go on the
internet and look up some symptoms, chat
chat check check check and say, oh, that
is me. That makes sense. But on the
other side of it, I do see how someone
who's been living with something and
trying to figure out what is wrong with
me.
Someone who's like, this why is it that
I'm struggling with friendships? Why is
it that I've always been struggling to
communicate? What is wrong with me?
There are a lot of people who are trying
to figure it out.
And with the use of different tools on
the internet have discovered, oh,
this is it. This makes sense. And the
benefits to me of self-diagnosing is
that now you have maybe the tools, the
insights. You can learn how to cope and
deal with whatever it is that you are
living with. Okay?
Now, okay, some people on the internet
are going to come for me and say like,
nope nope nope nope nope. What kind of
therapist is saying that it's okay to
self-diagnose?
I think sometimes it benefits people to
have something that makes sense. So many
people come to me and they're like, I
want the answer. Figure me out. Fix me.
What is going on with me? And there are
some people who need something to attach
to make sense. And there are other
people who are like,
I just want to figure it out just so I
can know. Okay? You have different types
of people.
What I think she should have done is go
on that show and say that I have been
realizing and connecting the dots that I
may be someone living with autism. Okay?
And that I have chosen not to
seek out a professional opinion because
I don't want to pay for it.
Okay? But either way, I feel like people
would account for her because they don't
like her.
The thing is people don't like Amanda.
Okay? They feel like she's a
professional victim. She blames
everybody else.
Once you have this kind of like arc,
viewpoint, these tropes that people
don't like about you, no matter what you
say, they're going to come for you.
Okay? People on the internet always got
time all day to be behind them keyboards
and you know, talking mess that they
wouldn't say to you in real life.
Okay? But when it comes to
self-diagnosing,
I do think it could be beneficial.
Depression.
So you guys really think that someone
should only go to a therapist to figure
out if they're depressed?
You know how hard it is to find a
therapist nowadays, how much it cost,
how many don't take insurance, how many
have wait list,
how many um charge like $300 an hour for
a session?
You know, access is very limited and
we're not talking about that. We're
focusing so much on self-diagnosing and
Amanda Seales, but not how the actual
medical system in Cal- not California,
in the US very much is not helping
people. Whether that's maternal black
health, whether that's trying to see a
doctor, you go to a doctor nowadays and
you went you literally this happened to
me. I have wait in a doctor's room for
30 minutes for the doctor to come in
only to touch me up for 5 or 10 minutes
and say, "Yeah, we just think it's
stress."
I waited in that room for how many
minutes? I drove here. I made the
appointment only for me to waste my time
and you tell me the things I'm dealing
with is stress. Okay? I could have saved
my time and went on Google and saw that
it was stress. Okay? So many times
American health system has shown us, we
don't care about you.
But you have people in the comments are
saying, put you need to put your trust
into a professional. Not only that,
sometimes these professionals don't
care.
There are good therapists out there,
there are bad therapists out there,
there are good doctors and there are bad
doctors, okay? How many people can say
that they have gone to a doctor recently
and really felt like the doctor,
psychiatrist, nurse was really focused
on them?
Making time for them and not just trying
to scoot them out the door so that they
can see the next 20 people waiting in
line.
That's what we're not talking about is
access and how much of a privilege it is
to have a therapist, a psychiatrist, to
be able to afford those things, okay?
There are a lot of people who don't have
access to those things, but we focus so
much on self-diagnosis. Well, if that
self-diagnosis saved somebody,
what if that self-diagnosis takes that
um those thoughts and feelings about
wanting to not be here anymore cuz you
finally figured out, oh,
it's depression. It's anxiety.
Oh,
maybe I'm living with bipolar disorder.
All these years people have been saying
I'm crazy, I'm mentally unstable,
something wrong with you. Well, mama, it
is something wrong with me. I'm living
with bipolar disorder.
And according to the things I've read on
the internet, okay? Somebody in our
genetic line also has probably been
living with bipolar disorder. I'm not
crazy, I'm not moody. There is something
that makes sense. And because now I know
that I'm living with bipolar disorder, I
can have a better life. But because we
are so focused on
the things about Amanda and the slip-up
of what she said, it was a mistake,
because now people are just like, "Oh,
we got something. Okay, we can get her
with. We can get it." But, I feel like
if it wasn't Amanda who had said it and
someone else had won that show and said
that they were self-diagnosed as
autistic, would have been such a big
deal? I really don't think so. Okay? So,
as a therapist, I see both sides. See
how self-diagnosing can benefit someone
and I see how it at times it can water
down the community of mental health,
psychologists thinking that, "Oh, I have
to do was just, you know, go online and
figure out that, "Oh, yeah, that's it
right there." Because that, you know,
person is living with it, I must be
living with it, too.
And that is not always accurate. So,
these are just my thoughts on
self-diagnosing.
I think the medical system has to get
better in order for people to have
access.
And access is a privilege that not
everyone has. But, of course, y'all
going to come in my comments and try and
get me together. So, do what you do.
Make sure you like, you subscribe. Let
me know your thoughts. Have you ever
self-diagnosed yourself with something
and felt like it made your life better?
Okay, on the other side of it, maybe it
made your life worse.
But, that's what it is. Some of these
people who are self-diagnosing, they
feel like it has made their life better.
Okay? Recognize your privilege in these
comments. Recognize the privilege you
hold in your day-to-day life that
somebody else does not have access to.
But, of course,
I got clients to see and I will see
y'all in the next video.